Inventory of the Meryle Secrest collection
Hoover Institution Archives
Meryle Secrest collection
1928-1994
1994
2001C50
Hoover Institution Archives
1 manuscript box, 2 CD boxes, 1 card file box (1.7 linear feet)
Sound recordings, notes, writings, clippings, and photographs relating to Svetlana Allilueva, daughter of Joseph Stalin, compiled by Meryle Secrest as working materials for an unfinished biography of Allilueva. Includes recorded interviews with Allilueva conducted in 1994.
Secrest, Meryle, collector
Access
Collection is open for research.
Use copies of all sound recordings in this collection are available for immediate access. For access to video recordings or motion picture material during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2001.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Scope and Content of Collection
The Meryle Secrest collection contains sound recordings, notes, writings, clippings, and photographs compiled by Secrest as working materials for an unfinished biography of Svetlana Allilueva. Included are Secrest's taped recordings of her interviews with Allilueva as well as her handwritten notes regarding the interviews. Also included are news clippings about Allilueva, Joseph Stalin, and Russia, photographs of Allilueva and her family, copies of autobiographical works by Allilueva, and copies of works translated by Allilueva related to her father, Joseph Stalin.
Svetlana Allilueva, also known as Svetlana Alliluyeva, Svetlana Stalina, and Lana Peters, was the youngest child and only daughter of Joseph Stalin and his second wife, Nadezhda Allilueva. In 1967, she defected to the United States after denouncing the Soviet Union, causing an international uproar. She briefly returned to the Soviet Union in 1984 after denouncing the United States, but eventually came back to the US. Allilueva passed away in 2011 in Richland Center, Wisconsin at the age of 85.
Biographical Note
Meryle Secrest is an award-winning biographer, mainly of artists and other prominent figures in the art world. She was born on April 23, 1930 in Bath, England. She was educated there, but later immigrated to Canada with her family. Secrest worked as a journalist for the Hamilton News in Ontario, where she was named "Most Promising Young Writer" by the Canadian Women's Press Club. In 1964, Secrest began writing profile interviews for the Washington Post, but left in 1975 in order to write books full-time.
Secrest's catalog of published works includes biographies of Frank Lloyd Wright, Salvador Dali, Stephen Sondheim, and Elsa Schiaparelli. She has received several awards for her work, including the American Library Association's George Freedley Memorial Award in 1999 and the Presidential National Humanities Medal in 2006. Her biography Being Bernard Berenson was a finalist for the Pulitzer Prize and the American Book Awards. In 2007, she published an autobiography titled, Shoot the Widow: Adventurers of a Biographer in Search of Her Subject.
Arrangement Statement
Materials are not organized into series; however, similar items have been grouped together.
Separated Materials
The book The Long Shadow: Inside Stalin's Family by Rosamon Richardson has been transferred to the Hoover Library.
Allilueva, Svetlana, 1925-; Stalin, Joseph, 1879-1953.; Defectors--Soviet Union.; Sound recordings.
- Interview notes, 1994 March (Box-folder 1: 1-2)
  Scope and Contents note
  Two notebooks with Secrest's handwritten notes regarding recorded interviews with Svetlana Allilueva (Lana Peters), organized by tape number. See Sound recordings section for information regarding use copies of the interview tapes.
- Clippings, 1967-1994 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  Newspaper and magazine clippings of articles on Russia, Stalin, and Svetlana Allilueva. Includes one article in Russian.
- Collected writings of Svetlana Allilueva, 1984-1993
  - "A Book for Granddaughters,", 1989 (Box-folder 1: 4)
    Typescript of an unpublished manuscript with edits throughout. Originally written in Russian and translated by Allilueva.
  - Curriculum vitae, 1993 October 29 (Box-folder 1: 5)
    Typed copy of Allilueva's curriculum vitae created for Secrest. Includes handwritten notes from "L. P." (Lana Peters).
  - The Faraway Music, 1984 (Box-folder 1: 6)
    Contains a photocopy of Allilueva's third book, sold only in India, Bangladesh, and Pakistan, in which she discusses disappointment with her American life after defecting from the USSR. Includes notes and annotations throughout. Also included is a copy of an article from The New York Times Book Review titled, "After the Crackup: Two Versions of Soviet History, Written with Anger and Enthusiasm."
  - "Statement of Svetlana Allilueva Made in Writing in the USA Embassy on March 6, 1967, in Delhi, India,", 1984 (Box-folder 1: 7)
    Photocopy of an excerpt from The Faraway Music.
- Works translated by Svetlana Allilueva, 1994
  - "Josef Is Infinitely Kind: Diary of Maria Onisimovna Svanidze," (Box-folder 1: 8)
    An unpublished English translation of Maria Svanidze's diary, with edits and notes throughout. Maria Svanidze was the wife of Alexander Semyonovich Svanidze, a personal friend of Stalin's and brother of Stalin's first wife, Ekaterine "Kato" Svanidze. In 1937, Alexander Svanidze was arrested by Stalin and shot four years later while imprisoned.
  - "To Nadezhda Sergeevna Allilueva Personally from Stalin," typescript (Box-folder 1: 9)
    Typescript of English translations of correspondence between Stalin and Nadezhda Allilueva, Svetlana Allilueva's mother, written between 1928 and 1931. Also included is a photocopy of an article from a Russian newspaper with annotations.
- Photographs, 1929-1994 (Box-folder 1: 10-11)
  Contains various black-and-white images of Svetlana Allilueva and her family. Envelopes A-E are located in Folder 10 and envelopes F-H in Folder 11. All images are copy prints with the exception of the photographs of Allilueva in London. Negatives of all images are also included.
  - Allilueva in London, 1994 March (Envelope A-B)
    Includes 11 prints plus duplicates and negatives.
  - Carolina Til (housekeeper) and Alexandra Bychkova (nanny), undated (Envelope C)
  - Gas mask drill at school, 1935
    Envelope reads, "Last one in the front line is Gerchikov."
  - Summer vacation with S.M. Kirov near Sochi, 1934
  - Allilueva with Katya (daughter) in the "House on the Embankment" apartment in Moscow, 1965
  - Allilueva at Lipki, 1940
  - Allilueva with Stalin in Sochi, 1934
  - Allilueva (age 3) at Zubalova near Moscow, 1929
  - Allilueva and brother, 1931 (Envelope D)
  - "Kirov at mother's coffin,", 1932
  - Allilueva in classroom, undated
  - Allilueva on lion at Lipki, undated
  - Allilueva as a child, in coat and beret, undated
  - Kumar Brajesh Singh in Moscow, 1965
  - Olga (daughter) in Allilueva's apartment, undated
  - Olga as a teenager, undated (Envelope E)
  - Allilueva with Olga (6 months) in Scottsdale, 1971 November
  - Allilueva with William Wesley Peters the day before their marriage, 1970 April
  - Portrait of Allilueva in Princeton, New Jersey, 1968 June
  - Olga and Allilueva, circa 1993-1994
  - Allilueva with Katya and Joseph (son), circa 1953-1954
  - Nadezhda Allilueva's funeral, 1932
  - Allilueva (age 12) at Stalin's dacha at Kuntsevo, circa 1937-1938 (Envelope F)
  - Svetlana and her best friend, Raya Levina, undated
  - Anna Allilueva (aunt), undated
  - Allilueva (age 16), undated
  - Allilueva on a bicycle at Kuntsevo, circa 1936-1937
  - Vyacheslav Molotov and Allilueva in the forest, undated
  - Pavel Alliluyev (uncle), undated
  - Portrait of Allilueva, 1954 (Envelope G)
  - Ketevan Geladze (Stalin's mother), undated
  - Portrait of Allilueva, 1943
  - Nadezhda Allilueva (age 30), undated
  - Maria Svanidze and others, circa 1930-1931
  - Allilueva with S.I. Hayakawa Scottsdale, Arizona, 1972
  - Nadezhda Allilueva and baby, undated
  - Svetlana with Emmanuel d'Astier near Fribourg, Switzerland, 1967 April (Envelope H)
  - Stalin and Nadezhda Allilueva at family picnic, 1929
  - Stalin with Allilueva in Sochi, 1934
  - Vasily Stalin (brother, age 13) and Allilueva (age 8), 1934
- Sound recordings, 1994 (Boxes 2-4)
  Consists of microcassettes as well as compact cassette and compact disc copies of interviews with Svetlana Allilueva, conducted by Meryle Secrest in March of 1994. The recordings have been digitized (see use copy reference numbers below) and are approximately one hour each.
  - Microcassettes (Box 2)
    - Tape 1, March 10
      General note
      Use copy reference number: 2001c50_a_0007768
    - Tape 2, March 10
      Use copy reference number: 2001c50_a_0007769
    - Tape 3, March 10
      Use copy reference number: 2001c50_a_0007770
    - Tape 4, March 10-11
      Use copy reference number: 2001c50_a_0007771
    - Tape 5, March 10-11
      Use copy reference number: 2001c50_a_0007772
    - Tape 6, March 11
      Use copy reference number: 2001c50_a_0007773
    - Tape 7, March 14
      Use copy reference number: 2001c50_a_0007774
    - Tape 8, March 14
      Use copy reference number: 2001c50_a_0007793
    - Tape 9, March 16
      Use copy reference number: 2001c50_a_0007775
    - Tape 10, March 16
      Use copy reference number: 2001c50_a_0007776
    - Tape 11, March 16
      Use copy reference number: 2001c50_a_0007777
    - Tape 12, March 17
      Use copy reference number: 2001c50_a_0007778
    - Tape 13, March 17
      Use copy reference number: 2001c50_a_0007779
    - Tape 14, March 17
      Use copy reference number: 2001c50_a_0007780
    - Tape 15, March 18
      Use copy reference number: 2001c50_a_0007781
    - Tape 16, March 18
      Use copy reference number: 2001c50_a_0007782
    - Tape 17, March 18
      Use copy reference number: 2001c50_a_0007783
    - Tape 18, March 21
      Use copy reference number: 2001c50_a_0007784
    - Tape 19, March 21
      Use copy reference number: 2001c50_a_0007785
    - Tape 20, March 21
      Use copy reference number: 2001c50_a_0007786
    - Tape 21, March 23
      Use copy reference number: 2001c50_a_0007787
    - Tape 22, March 23
      Use copy reference number: 2001c50_a_0007788
    - Tape 23, March 24
      Use copy reference number: 2001c50_a_0007789
    - Tape 24, March 25
      Use copy reference number: 2001c50_a_0007790
    - Tape 25, March 25
      Use copy reference number: 2001c50_a_0007791
  - Compact sound cassettes (Boxes 2-3)
    Contains one compact cassette copy of each microcassette.
  - CD sound discs (Boxes 3-4)
    Includes two CD copies of each microcassette.